hey what's going on guys so in this
video we're gonna create a development
workflow to compile the latest features
of JavaScript or equi script down to
browser runnable code so basically es5
which is the the version of javascript
that has been around forever and works
in all browsers alright so this is not
just to compile es6 or he is 2015 but
also es 2016 and es 2017 ok so even
features like a sink of weight we're
gonna be able to compile those down and
we're gonna do that by using webpack
along with babel and a couple of
different presets not only that but i'm
also going to show you how to set up web
pack dev server so that you can have a
server environment that you can work in
so you don't have to keep compiling down
loading your application and so on it'll
just constantly load in the browser
every time you save your file alright so
you're gonna learn quite a bit in this
video when it comes to web pack and
babble okay so let's get started this
video is sponsored by GPD host they
offer a variety of affordable hosting
plans with flexible billing cycles these
plans include a free ssl certificate a
free domain name website builder and
many other services including free
website migration with no downtime to
find out more visit GPD host com or
click the link in the description below
alright guys so very quick intro on web
pack I do have a crash course on my
channel if you're interested in that but
basically it's used to take modules with
dependencies and generate static assets
from them okay that way we can build
stuff with modules either custom that we
build ourselves or stuff that we install
from NPM and we can compile it down to
code that can run in the browser
alright so web pack is an amazing
technology it's what runs behind things
like the angular CLI the create react
app CLI it compiles everything from
those frameworks and its dependencies
down to static assets that can run in
the browser okay so it allows us to have
really intricate
and frameworks that can run without a
back-end server web pack uses presets
that can add extra functionality for
example there's a react preset to
compile react code
there's also presets for babbles such as
es 2015 2016 2017 but we're going to use
is a preset called babel n for env and
I'll get into that in a few minutes but
that's the gist of what web pack is all
right so now on to babble babble is a
compiler that will take features from
the latest versions of JavaScript or
echo script and bring them down to es 5
so real quick if we go up to try it out
then this is babble jst o / repple or
repl now here what we can do is put es6
+ code here and it'll get compiled over
here to es 5 so you can actually see the
conversion and what that looks like so
for instance if we were to use let which
is a way of declaring a block scope
variable and this is this is part of es6
or es2015
not available in es5 if we were to
create a variable here and just set it
and set it to 1 2 3 on this side you'll
see the es 5 version of this which uses
VAR kvar has been around since the
beginning of javascript it's let is not
part of es 5 so that's why it's being
converted alright now if we want to use
like an arrow function here so if we
want to go the console dot log and just
say 1 2 3 on this side you'll see not
only did it change let to var but it
also changed the arrow function to just
a standard function here that returns
the console log now when we set up web
pack with babel we're going to need to
use a preset okay and presets are
basically plugins and they have plugins
or presets for es 2015 which will
compile down es 2015 or es6 yes 2016
2017 and then they had this one called
latest which basically
all three of these together so that you
could compile down anything from any of
these but that's been deprecated in
favor of n for E and V which is this
right here
so this is what we'll be using and this
is very powerful because you can target
certain browsers certain versions you
can target certain features that you
want to use but we're just going to use
just a standard preset no configuration
nothing like that but that's what we'll
be using all right we're also gonna need
to use something called a polyfill which
I'll explain later on alright so enough
of the babel no pun intended and we're
gonna create a new folder here called
babel underscore web pack underscore
starter all right so we're gonna open
this with Visual Studio code or whatever
text editor you're using and let's go
ahead and open up a terminal now I'm
gonna be using my integrated terminal
with vs code so if you want to do that
you can go to view integrated terminal
or you can do control tilde and you can
toggle it that way
I also have get bash integrated with the
terminal so first thing we're gonna do
is run NPM in knit because we want a
package.json file now if you've never
worked with web pack before you're
probably wondering saying what are we
building a node.js application why are
we doing you know building up why are we
creating a package.json file well that's
what web pack does it allows you to use
NPM modules or your own modules and it
compiles them down to static assets so
that you can run it in the browser you
don't need a node server to run to run
that's the beauty of web pack so that's
what we're gonna do or I'm just gonna
create a simple package JSON file
real quick and let's open that up okay
we need to install a few dependencies
here a few modules so let's say npm
install and these should all be dev
dependencies so we want to do - - save -
dev alright we're gonna want to install
web pack you also want something
webpack - dev - server we want Babel
core we want the Babel loader for
webpack and we want the env preset so
that's babble - preset - env okay I
think that's everything for now so let's
run that alright so now what we want to
do is create a config file for web packs
so we're gonna go ahead and say new file
and let's call this web pack dot config
dot j s okay actually before we do that
I just want to add a script in package
dot Jason now a lot of tutorials will
tell you to actually install web pack
globally you do not have to do that what
you want to do is create a script here
I'm gonna call it build and then just
set that to web pack like that all right
we're gonna save that and that way when
we're ready to compile our java script
we can just say npm run build and that
will compile it down okay now this
config file is is where we're going to
define the source folder though the
source application the source file that
we're going to use and then the output
okay where do we want it to output into
es5 so first thing I'm gonna do is I'm
just gonna bring in a module called path
which is actually a core module so we
didn't have to install it or anything
and if you've used nodejs before you've
probably used path it's just for
manipulating file paths and things like
that so then we're gonna just do module
dot exports and set this to an object
and then this is where we define our
entry point so this is going to be an
object and we want to say app and then
in here is where we want to we want to
tell it which file we want to use to
basically be our source file
so I want to have us a folder called
source or SRC and then a file called app
dot J s okay so that's gonna be the
entry point to our application now what
we want to do is put a comma here we
want to put the output okay remember
we're having our app j s file which will
have es6 es seven you know all that
stuff all the new JavaScript features
and then it's going to be compiled down
to es five and that's where this output
is going to be okay so we want to
specify path and we're just gonna say
path dot resolved we're gonna use that
path module and we're gonna define
double underscored our name which just
means the current directory and then a
folder called build okay and you can
call this whatever you want I like to
call it build some people like to call
it dist
or output you can call it whatever you
want but we're gonna call it filled so
that's where I compiled JavaScript will
go now it needs a file name as well so
since it's going to be the app J s and
as well as any modules that we create
and we import into a PJs it's basically
going to be a bundle of JavaScript so
it's often called app or something like
app bundle dot GIS or just bundle J s
whatever you want to call it is fine but
that's what we're gonna call it so the
next thing we wanted to fine here is
module and this is where we define our
loaders so I wanna say loaders and
remember we installed that Babel loader
that's what we're gonna put here so this
needs to be an array we're gonna put in
an object here now the first thing we're
gonna have is test which is going to be
a regular expression okay so we're going
to use two slashes that's how we define
a regular expression literal and we're
just gonna say that we want to look at
all javascript files all dot j s files
so i'm going to put in the backslash
which is an escape character and then a
dot so that means that I want this dot
to be taken literally not as a meta
character
okay the escape is making it so it's a
literal dot then J s and then question
mark which makes it optional and then
the money sign which means it's the end
okay so it's the end any dot J's file
alright and then the next thing we want
is to put in exclude because we want to
we want to exclude the node modules
folder okay we don't want to do anything
with any node modules folder and then we
want to define the loader itself which
is going to be babel loader okay I
remember we installed that with NPM and
then we just want query and in query
which is an object this is where we
define our presets okay and presets is
gonna be an array and for now we're just
gonna put in env that's the preset that
we want to use so that's it that's our
entire config file for now so not too
hard to understand we have an entry
point for our es6 and es7 and whatever
else we wanted we want to write we can
use modules we can use whatever we want
from any standard and then it's going to
be output into build slash app bundle J
s and that's the file we want to include
in our HTML okay and then we just have
our babel loader as our module here as
our loader so let's save that and then
let's create a new folder called source
okay because remember we're gonna look
in source and then we're gonna look for
a pas so we're gonna create that and for
now what I'm gonna do is just put in
some I'll do the same thing I did in the
in the repple just to test equals one
two three actually we'll just set it to
an arrow
ah can't type the console dot log one
two three and save alright so what I
want to do now is compile this so if we
look in package dot Jason we created our
build script here so we should be able
to run this so let's open up our
terminal I'll clear it out we'll say NPM
run build all right so no red so no
errors everything should have one
alright so up here if we look we have a
build folder now creates automatically
we don't have to create it and then in
app bundle dot J s now there's going to
be a bunch of crap in here that doesn't
matter to us what we do want to look at
if we keep scrolling is this right here
okay so this is the code that we wrote
compiled so you can see that it used var
instead of let and it used a regular
function instead of an arrow function so
this es6 got compiled down to this es5
so this is going to work in all browsers
all right so this is what we want to
include in our HTML so what I'm gonna do
is create an HTML file in the root here
called index dot HTML and I'm just gonna
put some basic head body tags with Emmet
the title I'm just gonna say my
JavaScript app I'll just put h1 here
all right and then we want to go down
here and include a script with the
source of dot slash meaning we want to
look in the current directory for build
and then app dot bundle dot J s okay so
that's gonna look at our compiled file
that's what it's going to load so we'll
save that and now let's go to app J s
and let's just call test
ok so we'll save that and then we're
gonna recompile so npm run build and
then let's go and open up our index file
and let's hit f12 and we get one two
three all right so it's actually
compiling and it's loading into this
HTML file and if we look at our source
code click on this app bundle you'll see
our compiled es5 code alright so that's
how it works now keeping it like this is
gonna be kind of a pain in the ass
because every time you make a change
you're gonna have to recompile if we
change this to from one to three to
let's say hello and save and we open up
our index.html again and look in the
console we still get one two three all
right in order for that to change then
we'd have to go back and we'd have to
again run npm run build compile it and
then reload and then we get hello so
this is where web pack dev server comes
in so to do this this is actually really
easy all we have to do is go to web pack
config i'm sorry package jason and we're
gonna add another script here okay we're
gonna do a start script that way we can
just do npm start alright and then we
want to set this to
webpack - dev - server and then we need
to specify an output flag okay so we're
gonna say output actually output -
public - path and we want to set that
equal to whatever our output path was
which is build okay so we want to go
like that and then we'll go ahead and
save this and then go down here and
instead of running run build let's do
NPM start alright so now you can see
that this is actually started on port
I believe it's 8080 by default but I
think I have something running on that
already so let's go ahead and open this
up can I open it up like that I guess
not so let's go to localhost port 8081
and there's our application that favicon
will go away if I reload and it says
hello all right so I'm just gonna snap
this to the side here now this is going
to continuously run and continuously
watch our applications so if I go to app
j/s and I change this back to one two
three and save not only is it going to
reload it's also going to reload the
browser for us so we don't even have to
do that
so web pack dev server is a really nice
tool to have if you're working with web
pack so the idea is to use that until
you know you're ready to build and then
you do NPM run build you have your
static assets and you can upload to your
server or whatever it is you're doing
with your application alright so now
let's take a look at one of the reasons
why we're even doing this and that's to
use modules so let's clear this out and
what I'm gonna do is create in my source
folder a new file called Lib das okay
and this is going to be a module I want
to export something from this and import
it into App
which is something we cannot do just
within regular JavaScript within the
browser at least yet so what I'm gonna
do is say export and then I'm gonna
create a variable called person and I'm
gonna set this to an object literal and
just say name John Doe let's say
location Miami and age 30 all right so
we just have this person object and
we're exporting it okay exporting
meaning that we're making it available
to other files so let's save this let's
go back to AB js' and let's go ahead and
say import put some curly braces here
and say person from dot slash lib okay
we don't need the dot J s the file name
not the extension and then we'll go down
here and let's do alerts will say alert
person dot name and save and that should
reload and run and we get John Doe so
this John Doe this person dot name is
coming from another filed so this is
very very powerful when building
applications and gives you a more of a
you know a react or angular type feel
you can build applications that seem
like framework type applications rather
than putting everything in one file or
including a bunch of these script tags
with a bunch of different files so the
module system is very very powerful all
right and you can have other things you
can export other things here like let's
say we want to export a function so
we'll say export function say hello so
go like that and let's say this takes in
a name and then we'll say we'll just
return
and we'll use a template literal here
we'll just say hello name like that so
we'll save and then we can go back to
our ads that's gonna reload every time
we save maybe we should do a console log
and then what we can do is we're using
destructuring here and we can also pull
out other things from this file such as
say hello and then we'll go down here
and we'll call say hello and let's pass
in a name we'll just say Brad let's save
and down here whoops wait a minute
what'd I do
oh I got a since I just returned it here
we have to console.log the function so
we'll save and then we get John Doe
which comes from this line and then
hello Brad which comes from this and
both of these are coming from our Lib
Jas file here alright so that is modules
now I want to take a look at a newer
feature of es 2017 which is async/await
alright now I'm not going to go over the
over async/await and 10 really talk
about it I'm gonna do that in a
different video we're also going to be
talked about that and the new udemy
course coming out but it's just a better
way to handle asynchronous operations so
what we can do is we can say async we
can label a function asynchronous which
makes it return a promise automatically
I would say get posts
okay and then what I'm going to do is
create a variable here called response
and then I'm going to set it equal to
I'm going to use fetch to get something
from Jason placeholder which is
basically a fake REST API that we can
use I've used it in quite a few videos
but we can make requests to like this
post URL right here
so what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna say a
weight fetch and if you don't know what
fetch is it's pot it's a new standard in
the browser to make HTTP requests and it
returns data as a promise so since it
returns as a promise we're gonna say a
weight and then we're gonna pass in this
URL like that and then we're gonna say
right under it Const data and we can say
equals a weight response dot jason and
then we can return that data all right
why am I getting a error here oh I don't
have quotes in here okay so that's our
get put that's our get post asynchronous
function now to call this since it's it
we called it async then it's going to
return a promise so we say get posts and
with promises we use dot then and we'll
pass in here posts and then we'll just
console dot log posts all right so if we
go ahead and save this and we let this
run we're gonna get an error so we get
this regenerator run time is not defined
and to fix this we actually need to use
the babel polyfill all right if I were
to search this see what we get if we
search this error here
right here I'm trying to use async await
with Babel six
so right here Babel polyfill is required
you must use that in order to get why is
this not responsive
why is Stack Overflow not responsive but
you'll see that we need to install Babel
polyfill along with this Babel preset
stage zero and then down here we need to
add that to our web pack config file
okay so let's do that let's go ahead and
ctrl C stop this webpack dev server and
we're gonna do NPM install - - save -
dev and we want to install babel - poly
fill as well as babel - shoot what was
it i always forget this one babel preset
stage - zero alright so install those
two things now that by itself isn't
gonna work we need to go to our web pack
config file and from here we want to add
on to the app in the entry so I'm just
gonna put I'm gonna go right above it
and we're just gonna put in some quotes
and we're gonna say babble - polyfill
and then a comma and then down here with
our presets we just want to include that
stage zero preset alright and that
should do it so let's save let's go back
over here and let's run NPM start let's
have our page up here and run NPM start
ok looks like we got an error unexpected
token where is this let's see what did I
do wrong here Babel polyfill
oh I did this idiot this goes in here so
app and then this should be an array and
we'll put that in there like that
yeah that should do it so let's save
that let's try it again and Pam start
okay let's reload and there we go if we
look down here we're now fetching our
post so this is coming from right here
our async/await
get post function we're returning a
promise here getting the post and we're
logging them so you can see that now
this can be used this this web pack
babble starter package can be used to
compile down anything from es2015 1617
to es 5 so it's something that you can
continuously use and hopefully you guys
will use it now as far as compiling like
let's say you just built an awesome
application with modules with a sink of
weight and all that all you got to do is
now simply do and where is it npm run
build and then it builds it out into
that app bundle file you have your
index.html file so you could simply
let's say this is your web server you
could just take the build and the
index.html go in there open up your file
and let's open up our console and we
have our posts ok and we're using it's
all compiled down to this one file and
you could have you could have 30
different modules it would still all
compile down to that one file alright so
hopefully you guys enjoyed this and
that's it thanks for watching
hey guys I just want to mention our
sponsor GPD host so if you're looking
for affordable fast and quality cpanel
hosting look no further they offer many
types of packages
that include a free domain name free SSL
certificate a website builder and more
all hosting plans are completely managed
and easy to work with
you also get automatic weekly backups so
whether you have a website to transfer
or you're building it from scratch GPD
host is a high quality solution to learn
more visit GPD host comm or click the
link in the description below