hey what's going on guys this
mini-course is going to be an
introduction to rxjs and reactive
programming so rxjs stands for reactive
extensions for JavaScript reactive
extensions or reactive X is a library
for working with asynchronous data
streams and observables alright all the
content in this video is covered much
more thoroughly in the full course
available from edge wanax so if you like
this video I would strongly suggest
checking that out and I'll leave a link
in the description so what is reactive
programming most of you have probably
already worked with it ok you just don't
know it yet if you've worked with
angular 2 rxjs and observables are
pretty big part of that all right so if
you google reactive programming you will
find some information but a lot of it is
really vague or theoretical or too
complicated so the purpose of this edge
Ronix course in this video is to give
you some really some solid practical
examples
all right so reactive programming is a
programming paradigm that works with
asynchronous data streams and these data
streams can come from or be created by
many different things so things like UI
events like clicks or key presses HTTP
requests file systems array like object
strings and even your machines memory
and cache ok these things can be turned
into or can be viewed as a data stream
so a stream is defined as a sequence of
ongoing events ordered in time and
there's a few things we can get from a
stream so we can get the data that it
emits which could be virtually anything
and any kind any type of data we can get
errors if something goes wrong and then
we can get a signal that notifies us
when it's complete if in fact it does
complete some of them don't so if we
look at this image right here represents
a stream so we start with some kind of
event indicates an event with some kind
of value for example coordinates of a
click all right so moves along the
stream if
something goes wrong it can send off an
error which can notify we can have our
application react to that our ok and
then it keeps going and it can send off
a signal when it's complete now some
streams won't complete for instance most
movements you can get a stream from most
movements and obviously those don't
complete they're just going to keep
going as long as you move the mouse
whereas something like an HTTP GET
request you're going to get the data
it's going to come through in the stream
and it's going to complete now the way
that we work with these streams is with
what's called an observable so
observables are used to watch these
streams and they'll emit a function when
the value is emitted or an error or a
complete signal is returned
so observables can be subscribed to by
an observer and there's no limit to how
many subscriptions and observable can
have so we can interact with these data
streams as if they were just a regular
array we can use array like methods and
we have a whole bunch of operators that
will allow us to manipulate the data
pretty much however we want so right now
we can't just use standard JavaScript
es5 or even es6 to work with observables
and streams and reactive extensions is
what allows us to do that which is also
sometimes called reactive X all right so
it's a library for composing
asynchronous programs by using
observable sequences and it provides us
with a long list of operators which
allow us to filter select transform
combined and compose observables now
reactive extensions is not limited to
just JavaScript if you look at this list
you can see that it's available for many
of the popular programming languages of
all types now the reason I chose
JavaScript and rxjs is because
javascript is a well-known language the
rxjs library is pretty stable and goes
in-depth in terms of what you can do
with it and also that's JavaScript is
happens to be what I specialize in so
that's what we'll be using throughout
this video and throughout the
reactive extensions course alright so
before we get started let's just take a
look at exactly what we'll be covering
here so I'll show you how to observe and
examine asynchronous data streams that
come from UI events will create
observables from array like objects will
create observables from scratch we'll
learn how to filter and transform
observables how to create observables
from promises and we'll look at some of
the really helpful operators that the
reactive extensions library gives us and
then we'll take a look at error handling
all right so that's it let's go ahead
and jump in and start to take a look at
some code alright so we're going to
start out with creating our environment
and there's just a few things that I
want to explain before we get started so
this is the reactive X website reactive
X dot IO and this is the main API for
reactive extensions which is available
in many different languages so if we
click on choose your platform you can
see all the different languages that the
library is available for now we're using
JavaScript so we're using rxjs now if I
click on that it'll bring us to the
github page and this is for it's
important to note that this is for
version 4 all right we're going to be
using version 5 which isn't beta but it
is very stable alright so the I mean the
most of the API is the same but there
are a few operators that have been
changed in rxjs 5 but notice that
version 4 is at github reactive
extensions slash rxjs
version 5 is at github reactive X slash
rxjs and you can see this is version 5
so if you're looking for the doc for
documentation this is where you want to
be all right if you're if you're
following along with this course now the
migration guide right here says
migrating from 4 to 5 if I click on that
it'll just show you the rxjs for
operators and what the what the version
5 operators what they've been changed to
all right now as far as our environment
you can just use an HTML file and
include the rxjs main javascript this is
a list of the CDNs now you'll see that
it's broken up into different aspects
but what you want to do is include if
you're going to use a CDN you want to
just include the RX dot all J s and
notice that this is version 4 if you're
following along you're going to want to
choose the latest version of 5 in this
case it's beta 12 all right so you just
want to include one of these either the
minified or the regular alright but
we're not going to use a CDN we're going
to be using a an environment using
webpack and babel now initially I was
going to go through all the steps to set
that up but it was too time-consuming
and I really want to just focus on rxjs
and observables in them in the actual
course from adju annex I do go through
and show you exactly how to set it up
but in this case we're going to just
grab it from github alright so if you go
to github.com slash brad traversée
slash rxjs underscore boiler and it's
pretty easy to set up okay so we just
need to install our dependencies we need
to compile the JavaScript of web pack
and we can run it in watch mode so that
it updates every time we save the file
and then we just need to install live
server and run it glow run NPM start so
let's go ahead and do that now you can
you can clone it with git or you can
just download it I'm just going to
download the zip file here alright and
let's go ahead and open that up and then
what we want to do is just create a
folder to work in and I'm just going to
call this our XJS sandbox alright and
then we're just going to bring
everything over alright and I'll go
through the files really quick it's
pretty simple we're using webpack along
with babel now if we look at the
package.json file you'll see that for
dependencies we
have bable bable core in bevel loader
also the preset to compile from es2015
because we want to be able to use the
latest javascript and then compile it
down to more compatible version and of
course web pack which is going to allow
us to use modules and so on and then our
regular dependencies of course we have
rxjs and then we're also going to use
jQuery so that we can easily select
elements all right so that's what will
be installed when we run npm install all
right and then we have a web pack config
file basically we're saying that our
javascript file we want to work with is
in the source folder fjs and when we run
web pack it will compile it into the
dist folder into a file called app
bundle j/s and that's what we'll include
in our HTML all right and then down here
we're just specifying that we want to
use babel and we want to use the es2015
preset all right so that's what's going
on there and that's pretty much it in
the source folder we have our app j/s
that's the main file we'll be working
with and yeah so i'm going to open up
sublime text and let's go ahead and add
this folder to
add this as a project okay so desktop
sandbox and there we go
alright so in the app j/s right now
we're just importing jQuery and we're
also importing rxjs and then we're just
doing a consult log so let's go ahead
and run npm install so i'm going to open
up a command line okay or open up your
command line or you went your linux
terminal Mac whatever you're using and
let's navigate to that folder
all right and we're going to go ahead
and run npm install and of course you
need to have no js' installed if you
don't just go to node.js org and go
ahead and download and install it all
right so you can see that it created the
node modules folder and it's now
installing the dependencies alright so
now that that's done we're going to
we're going to compile our JavaScript or
we're going to run web pack in watch
mode so let's run web pack - w and what
that will do is take that app.js file
and compile it into the dist folder okay
so if we look now we have a dist folder
with app bundle J s so that's the file
that is being included in the index file
if we open that up you'll see it's being
included right here now we're also going
to want to install live servers so that
we can run this in a server environment
so I'm going to open up another command
line
okay let's navigate to that folder
okay and let's install live server
globally so NPM install live server -
gee all right so now we should be able
to simply run NPM start and that will
open up the localhost port 8000 all
right you can see we're getting our
index page and if we open the console
with f12 you see that we have our XJS
boiler running so everything is now set
up and we're ready to start to code with
rxjs
alright guys so the first thing we're
going to do is we're going to create an
observable sequence from UI events okay
a couple different types of events so
first thing I'm going to do I have my
app.js file open and my index.html I'm
going to create a button all right I'm
going to get rid of this and let's say
button and we'll give it an ID of BTN
okay we'll say click save that and live
server will automatically reload which
is nice alright and we can get rid of
this console log and first thing we want
to do is create a variable for that
button so I'm going to say Const BTN
equals and this is where a jQuery comes
in we want the ID of BTN okay now what
we'll do is create a variable for the
observable and for the first stream so
let's say Const and we'll call it BTN
stream money sign now the money sign
isn't required but it is good practice
that way you know which of your
variables is an actual observable and
represents a stream all right so we're
going to set that to our X dot
observable and then we're going to use
the from event operator alright now this
is going to take in a couple parameters
first one is going to be the actual
element so BTN and the next one will be
the
type of event we want which is going to
be a click in this case alright so
that's all there is to creating an
observable ok we're creating it from the
event now what we need to do is
subscribe to it ok you need to subscribe
to observables so we're going to say BTN
Stream money sign dot subscribe alright
and then in here it's going to take in
three functions one is going to be to
return the stream of the data in the
stream the next one will be to return
any errors if there are any and the last
one will be will run when it's completed
if it does complete so let's go ahead
and put function and just going to put
this on another line alright now we can
pass in whatever we want for a variable
here I'm going to use e for event and
then what we'll do is just console dot
log and for now I'm just going to
console.log clicked alright and then
we're going to have another function
which will take in ever and this will
only run if there's some kind of error
okay we just want to console log it and
then the last one is for when it
completes and we're just going to
console dot log and I'll say completed
alright so let's go ahead and save that
and that should reload and then if I
click on it you'll see we get clicked ok
now obviously this isn't very helpful so
what we want to do is pass in that eval
you alright so let's save that and now
we click and you can see what we get
this this large object that has all
these values alright so you can kind of
look at you can look at elements as
having their own little mini database ok
with all these different values so you
can see we have the timestamp we have
the original event which if we open that
has a whole bunch of other stuff
if the target can see we can get the the
element and its ID we can get the class
name there isn't one but if there was we
could get that we can get the client
height client position the innerhtml
which is the text of the button the ID
we can get all this stuff so for
instance if we want to get what's in the
inner HTML we can say e dot target dot
inner HTML and we'll save that and you
can see now we're getting the click
alright if I was to change that to click
one and click we get click one all right
so just a way to get some of these event
values so now what I want to do is use a
different of kind of event so let's
create an input box a text box
okay so put let's just put a HR tag
there and then we'll say input type
equals text and we'll give it an ID of
input okay and whips don't want to do
that all right and then what we'll do is
in our app J s so let's create a
variable called input and we're going to
set that equal to jQuery and we want the
ID input all right and then what I'm
going to do is just copy this this
button stream and let's change it to
input stream and change this value to
input and then we're going to change the
actual event to key up all right and
then down here we'll replace that with
input okay now I should mention that the
only required the first function here is
the only required one we don't need to
do the error we don't need to do the
completed all right and you may have
noticed that the key of these events
don't fire off completed because they
don't complete you know if
if you have a click event you can keep
having click events it's not something
that ends such as an array or get
requests it's going to get some data and
then complete all right it's ongoing so
let's go ahead and we're going to just
get rid of this target in our HTML and
let's save that and now if I go and I
start to type you can see that every
time we type a character it brings up
that event ok so this is a constant
stream of data now if we want to let's
say we want to get the actual values
being typed in we can get that from
current target and value or is it right
here value all right so let's do that
we'll say console.log e dot current
target dot value and we'll save that and
now you'll see that as I type it'll give
us the value down in the console all
right and we can actually get this from
a target value too
all right so we're getting a constant
stream that is giving us whatever we
type into the input box and of course if
we wanted to we could output that in the
browser window in the body so if we
create an div here and let's give it an
ID of output okay we'll save that and
then we'll just create a variable for it
and then down here let's say output dot
append okay so now we're using jQuery
and we'll pass in a dot target dot value
so let's save that now if we go and
click in here and start to type you'll
see that it's going to output in the
browser all right so this works similar
to how angular 2 works with its data
binding so there's one more event that I
want to show you and that's the
mousemove event so let's go ahead and
grab this and let's change it to will
just say move stream and change this to
document because I want this to work on
the entire document and then we'll
change the event we're going to change
that to mouse move all right and then
down here let's just keep that as is
actually no we don't want to keep it as
is let's do output dot append and we
want the x and y values so we'll say X
and then we'll concatenate onto that e
dot client X all right and then we'll
say Y and then client Y all right so if
we save that and I go in the document
it's all we need to change this to move
straight
and it should be a dot client why so
let's save that and now as I move around
you'll see that to capture my
coordinates now I don't want this to
just keep adding to it I want it to
replace it every time it gets those
values so let's change I'll put a pen to
output I will say output dot HTML and
we'll add an h1 around these alright so
if we save that now when we move around
you'll see that it outputs in the
browser so it's a constant stream giving
us the this data this X&Y coordinates
all right so that's how we can create
observables from events alright so now
that I've showed you how to create
observables for events now I'm going to
show you how to create them from array
like objects all right so I've cleared
everything out and I will be I will post
the files on github and I'll add a link
in the description but I just clue I
cleared out everything from there and
also the index.html alright so what
we're going to do is we're going to
create a simple array of numbers all
right so we have these numbers and we
want to create an observable sequence
from these numbers so let's say Const
we'll call this numbers money sign and
set this to our X dot observable and
we're going to use the from operator all
right and then we'll just stick in their
numbers all right so we want to
subscribe to this observable so let's
say numbers money sign dot subscribe and
in the last video we just used our
callback functions now I'm going to show
you how to use arrow functions which is
just a different way to to add these
callbacks all right so let's say for the
the actual values we'll use V and we'll
set that to
Eero function - a code block all right
it's all preference you can do the other
way or you can use the arrow functions
so we'll say console dot log V alright
and then for the next one we'll say
error set that console dot log error
whoops
alright and then for our complete this
console dot log and we'll just put in
the string completed all right so let's
go ahead and save that and see what
happens so you'll see that it's taking
that array and it's outputting as an
observable sequence now notice with this
one we're actually getting completed we
didn't get that with from event because
the the events don't stop this however
is just a static array when it gets to
the end it's going to run the completed
all right now usually you'd probably be
working with some kind of data source
that that outputs Jason are an array of
JSON objects so let's do that I'll say
Const post and we'll set that to an
array and say the posts have a title and
a body
all right we'll add a couple more of
these all right so we have these posts
and then we're just going to say Const
we'll do post money sign equals our X
dot observable dot from and we'll paste
in here or we'll type in here posts and
I'm just going to copy this and change
that to posts and if we go ahead and
save that we're going to get the objects
okay which have a title and a body all
right now if we want to output this up
here we can do that pretty easily
let's do will say ul will give it an ID
of posts all right and that's it we'll
save it and then over here we'll go down
and we can even make this a little more
descriptive and say post and then let's
do the ID posts and say dot append and
here we'll put our allies let's do post
dot title all right and actually we'll
wrap that also in an h3 all right and
then after that let's put a paragraph
and then we'll just concatenate in there
post dot body all right so let's save
that and whoops we need to change that
and there we go so now we're grabbing
the objects and we're out putting the
the title on the body of each post
now we're not limited to just standard
arrays we can even use sets and maps so
let's just comment all this stuff out
all right and let's create a set now a
set is basically an array that can have
any type of data it can have strings or
numbers or objects so let's say Const
set and we'll set it to new set and
let's pass in here some brackets and
we'll put in a string put in a number
and put in an object all right and then
we can create a stream from that I'm
actually going to just copy this
alright let's change this to our set
stream it will pass in set change that
and let's get rid of this line and we'll
just console.log that and I'm just going
to change this back to V alright so
let's go ahead and save and now you can
see we get our string our number and
then our object and it also fires off
completed so that's how you can create
an observable from a set you can do the
same with map and a map is basically an
array of key value pairs so I'm going to
just paste this in and we'll change this
to map change that and inside our
brackets we'll set another pair of
brackets we'll say 1 2 3 4 and 5 6 ok
we'll change this to map
and save and now it outputs our key
value pairs so that is the from operator
all right so we've learned how to create
observable sequences from events and
from array like objects now I'm going to
show you how to create an observable
from scratch so I've cleared everything
out and we're going to create a variable
called source money sign and we're going
to set that to new rx dot observable all
right and then we're going to pass in
here I'm just going to use arrow
functions here we're going to use an
observer all right and then let's just
do a console dot log and we'll just say
creating observable all right so let's
leave that for now and subscribe to it
so source dot subscribe all right and
we're going to pass in here let's say
we'll use X console.log X and let's do
the other two
and complete okay so let's go ahead and
save that all right so we get creating
observable now this is just console
logging we're not actually emitting
values yet so if we want to emit a value
then we need to take that observer and
call dot next alright and if you've ever
used a JavaScript generator function
this is pretty similar so let's say
observer dot next and we'll just say
hello world all right so let's go ahead
and save that and you can see that we're
now emitting hello world if we want to
emit another value from the stream will
say observer dot next and we'll say
another value save it and we get another
value now just to show you that this is
in fact a stream that is constantly open
let's do a timeout we'll do set timeout
and pass in here just an arrow function
and we'll do observer dot next and we'll
say yet another value and let's set the
timeout here to three seconds so 3,000
milliseconds and we'll save it so we
should get the first two values and then
three seconds later it emits yet another
value so you can see that it's a it's an
open stream now notice that we didn't
get the completed and the reason for
that is because we actually have to make
the observer complete so we're going to
go right under the last next we did and
say observer
complete and we'll save that okay three
seconds later we're going to get that
value and then it completes now if I
were to put this complete outside of the
set timeout it would complete before
this run so you want to make sure if you
do something like this you want to
complete at the right at the right place
so now errors if we want to let's say
have some kind of conditional and if it
fails we want to set an error so we
could say observer dot error and in here
we'll say new error and you can put
whatever you want here to output will
just say error and we'll say something
went wrong all right so if we save it
you see we get our error now notice that
it doesn't complete when our error shows
up it just just kind of stops now if we
want we can make this a little more
user-friendly and we can add down here
dot catch and we can pass in here error
and we'll set that to rx dots observable
and use of now what of does is it just
takes whatever you pass in and use in
sets that as an observable all right so
it just takes in arguments and fires it
off as an observable so we're going to
pass in an error all right so now if we
save that we get our error but you can
see that it does in fact go on to
complete all right so just a more
friendly way of handling things handling
errors so that's how you can create a
observable from scratch alright so now
I'm going to show you how to create an
observable sequence out of a promise
okay a promise basically represents the
eventual result of an asynchronous
operation okay so it does something and
then it can get a return of value and it
can return
at a later time using dot then so let me
just give you an example of a really
simple promise
so we'll say Const my promise and we're
going to set that to new promise and in
here it'll take in a callback I'm just
going to use an arrow function so it'll
take resolve and reject all right and
then let's just do console dot log and
it'll say creating promise and we want
to run resolve and then return out value
so what I'm going to do is just do a set
timeout okay so usually you would have
some kind of asynchronous operation
happen but we're just going to set a
timeout and then we're going to call
resolve and we're going to emit some
kind of value we'll just say hello from
promise all right and we'll set the
timeout to three seconds so there's a
very simple promise now we could get it
by saying my promise dot then all right
and then inside then little console dot
log X so it works very similar to an
observable so let's save that and
creating promise in three seconds we
should get hello from promise all right
now if we want to take this and return
as an observable let's let's comment
this out and we'll do Const source our X
dot observable and then we want to use
the from promise operator all right and
then we can pass in my promise
so now let's subscribe to it don't say
source
dot subscribe and let's just do console
dot log X okay so let's save it and then
we should get the same result okay three
seconds later we get hello from promise
all right so let's do something a little
more useful what I want to do is I'm
going to send it an ajax request to the
github api to get some information on a
user so I'm going to first create a
function called get user alright and
this is actually from the edge' wanax
course this is going to be a much
lighter version of that in the course we
actually create a kind of a mini
application and make it look really nice
but this is going to be just really
quick so I'm going to say get user
username and then we want to return
we're going to use jQuery and use the
Ajax method here and let's pass in a URL
which is going to be HTTP API dot
github.com slash users slash and then
we'll just concatenate the user name
alright and then we also want a data
type alright and since we're on a
different domain we're going to use
JSONP as our data type now we want this
returned as a promise so we can use dot
promise and now let's go down here and
we're going to say Const so let's not
even put it in a variable we'll just do
our X dot observable dot from promise
okay and we're going to pass in here
that function get user
all right and for the username we'll
just pass in my username all right and
we can actually just subscribe to it
like this I've been using variables but
you can do it this way
so we'll say dot subscribe and let's do
console
I'm not console we want to do X let's
see X and then console dot log X all
right so let's see what that gives us
we'll save it and you can see we get
this object it has data and data object
and meta so if we open up data you can
see that we're getting all this
information about this github user and
we can grab this and put it in our HTML
if we want so let's do I will say h1
give it an ID of name and let's say we
want to get let's see we'll get the the
blog URL right here so we can do
we'll say ul Li with the ID of blog and
then let's also get the public the
number of repos so we'll put an li give
it an ID of repos all right so let's go
ahead and save that and then in our app
J s we'll go down here and let's do
what was that name and we'll say dots
text and we want that x value and then
it has a data object so we want to say
dot data and then dot name all right and
then we'll do the blog so that's data
dot blog and then the public repos all
right and let's just add some text in
here to will say public repos all right
so save that and there we go so we're
pulling out the name we're pulling out
the blog URL and that should actually be
public repos public underscore repos all
right now let's do something a little
more interesting we're going to create
an input form where we can change the
user name and have that output I'll put
the result as a stream so we'll go to
our HTML and let's put in up here and
input give it a type of text and an ID
of input all right so I'm going to go
right above this and we're going to
create a variable called input source
okay we'll set that to our X dot
observable and we're going to use from
event okay and for the selector we'll
just use our jQuery here and say input
and then the event itself we're going to
do key up all right so now let's
subscribe to that
all right and in here we'll go like that
and then we'll just copy this or we'll
cut it rather and paste it right in
there and then instead of passing in
just a static username we're going to
pass in here e dot target dot value so
whatever we type in the input now I do
want you to note that doing this this
double subscribe here and here isn't
really the way you want you would want
to do this you want to use something
like merge map or switch map but I'm not
going to get into that now so for now
we're going to leave it like this
alright we'll do that later so let's go
ahead and save that and now as I type it
should fetch the data wait a minute he
is not defined
oh let's change that to E all right so
save that and then I put a B in and
that's what's going to come back for the
username B from the github API if we put
Brad and that's Brad pitcher we get and
as I type mine when we get to it my name
shows up all right so it's very dynamic
and in the full course we do this but we
actually build out a nice interface that
uses bootstrap that uses the Avatar and
all that stuff all right so that's going
to be it for promises in the next video
we're going to take a look at some
operators we're going to look at
interval timer and range all right so
we're going to take a look at interval
timer and range okay and these are
really helpful for just testing and just
learning in general all right so we'll
start with interval and what this does
is it returns an observable sequence
that produces a value after each period
all right so let me give you a quick
example so we'll create a variable
called source and let's set it to our X
dot observable dot interval alright and
this is going to take in one parameter
which is going to be the length of time
between each emission all right so let's
say one second 1000 milliseconds and
then we'll subscribe to that okay and
we're going to pass in here X and
console dot log X all right so let's go
ahead and run that and you can see that
it waits a second then it starts firing
these off from 0 up and it's going to be
a second in between each emission all
right if I were to change this to let's
say three we'll save that and now the
interval will be three seconds apart
okay now this will just keep going on
forever if you want to specify specify
an end point we could use the take
operator so we'll say take I will say
take five okay we'll run it at let's do
a hundred milliseconds so that'll be
even faster alright so you can see that
it goes from zero to four now we put
five in but it only goes to four because
it's zero based okay so it gets five
five values and let's actually put our
error and complete functions as well
all right so let's try running that
again and you see that we do get a
completed at the end all right if we
don't if we didn't use take it would
just keep going it wouldn't complete all
right so the next one I want to look at
is timer so I'm going to just copy this
whole thing and let's comment it out
okay so we'll change this to timer so
this will emit one particular item after
span of time that we specify so let's
put in here 1000 and 1000 and we'll see
what that gives us okay so that's
basically going to work how interval
works okay we can set the time from when
the page loads to when it starts so if
we want to say five seconds and then the
time from in between each one we say two
seconds and we save that now it's not
going to start for five seconds and then
when it does it's going to wait two
seconds in between each one all right so
very similar to interval and then the
last one I want to look at is range so
we'll go ahead and copy this
okay we'll change this to range and we
don't need to take five on this because
we actually set a start and stop part so
we're going to say start at zero and go
five five values up all right so let's
save it okay and you can see that it all
gets emitted at once and it completes so
if we were to set the
from let's say 25 and then 100 save that
okay so what it does is it starts at 25
and then goes 100 from that so that gets
all the way up to 124 and then it
completes all right so very simple but
as you'll see as we move along and if
you take the course these are very
valuable in terms of development testing
and learning all right so now we're
going to take a look at a really useful
and common operator and that's map
alright we'll also look at pluck which
is kind of a simpler version of map so
what map does is it applies a function
to each item that's emitted by the
source observable and it returns an
observable that emits the results of the
of that function okay so we can
essentially take any of the data that's
emitted and just manipulate it in many
different ways
alright so let's do a simple example
here we're going to create a variable
called source and let's set that to our
X dot observable dot interval okay and
for the interval let's say one second
and then we'll take source and subscribe
alright and in here
let's see you know what let's some no
that's fine
so we're going to take that value and
just console.log it
okay so let's also add a take here so it
doesn't go on forever
we'll say dot take ten all right so save
that and then it's just going to start
at zero and every one second go to ten
okay so we already understand that now
let's say that we want to take each
value and we want to double it all right
so what we could do is up here we'll say
dot map actually let's put it after take
okay we'll say dot map and here we'll
pass in V and we'll set that to a code
block and actually we'll keep it on this
line so we don't need a code block we'll
just save V multiplied by V all right so
now let's save it and we get zero one
four nine sixteen so what actually I
said double but we're actually
multiplying it by itself all right if we
wanted to double it then we would times
it by two and we get we should get two
four six eight so on alright so we can
manipulate the data however we want all
right let's take a look at an example
that's not math all right so let's say
Const
source is going to equal rx doc
observable and let's do from okay so
we're going to do it from an array so
I'm going to pass in just an array of
names John Tom and Sean okay so we have
these names and let's stop it there and
then we'll just subscribe to it
okay we'll just pass in V and we'll just
do console dot log V okay so obviously
that's just going to give us this this
array of names as an observable sequence
now let's say we want to make all these
names uppercase so what we could do is
add on to it dot map and let's set the
and we'll set it to V dot to uppercase
all right let's save it okay so it will
reload and now you can see that all the
names are uppercase now we're not
limited to just having one map we can
add as many as we want so let's add
another one and in this one let's just
add the text I am before each name so
we'll say map V and let's set that to a
string we'll say I am and then we'll
concatenate on V okay so save that and
now we get I am John Tom and Sean
alright so we can have as many maps as
we want alright let's take a look at
another example I'm going to use the
github function that we used in the
promises section so I'm going to paste
this in so we have our get github user
returning a promise we're using from
promise and we're subscribed we're
getting this user okay so let's see what
that gives us okay so it just gives us
an object which has a data object which
then has the user information all right
so if we wanted to we could add a map
here so if we say dot map and then we'll
say user and we could set that to user
dot data
and that way you could actually get rid
of that data object so if we save that
it'll pass us the actual object now if
we want to be more specific let's say we
just wanted the name out of this we
could go ahead and say name set that to
user dot data name and we could create
that change this to name you don't have
to but it's more descriptive and save it
and let's say user not defined also
actually you know what this should stay
user so we'll save that and now we just
get the name so now let's take a quick
look at pluck okay I'm just going to
comment this stuff out and what I'm
going to do is create a lot of our
consulates call this users this is just
going to be an array of users and I'm
just going to paste this in okay so we
have these three users with a name and
age so let's go ahead and create a user
stream alright so pass in users and
let's do users subscribe we'll say X
okay so let's save that and that's just
going to give us these users as a stream
as an observable now let's say that we
want to pluck out just the name okay we
want to return just names so what we
could do is just add on to this
we'll say dot pluck and then we'll just
pass in name okay save that and now it's
just going to give us the names okay we
could get any value we want if we want
the ages we can do that as well
all right so that is map and pluck all
right so we're going to quickly look at
merging concat now merge is it allows us
to merge two are more observables and
can cattle aoz us to concatenate them
which means one right after another all
right so let's start with merge now
let's do our X dot observable and we're
going to just use the of operator which
just takes whatever you pass it and
turns that into an observable so let's
say hello all right and then let's
subscribe to it okay console.log X and
we need to go like that all right so
let's go ahead and save that and that's
just going to give us hello now let's
say we want to merge another observable
onto it so to do that we can say dot
merge and in here we'll do our X dot
observable dot of and put in every one
okay so now let's save that and we now
get observers the two together so let's
take a look at another example using
interval all right so let's do rx
dot observable dot interval and we'll
say two seconds take 25 and subscribe
okay notice I'm doing at the shorthand
way now because we are running out of
time
alright so in here let's do console dot
log what i keep doing that i keep
forgetting my arrows so console dot log
x so we know what that's going to do
it's going to start at zero and go to 24
after every two seconds it'll emit okay
so let's say that we want to merge in
another interval so we'll say dot merge
and our X dot observable dot interval
and this time let's do it every half a
second alright so now it's hard to tell
which one is which but we have the one
running every half a second which starts
first and then it goes zero one two and
then two seconds later this one starts
at zero while this one's still going
three four five six and then that runs
again the two second one at one and it
keeps going like that so we're having
two of these run they're merged together
they're running at the same time now
there is a different and better syntax
we could use with merge so let's take a
look at that alright so let's say we
have source will say source one and
we'll set that to our X dot observable
got interval every two seconds and let's
do a map onto it okay so say map and
we'll say V and
we'll say merge one and then concatenate
that V alright that way we'll be able to
identify them so let's copy that and
then right below it will do large - and
this one will be every half a second all
right we'll call this source - and then
what we can do is we can say our X dot
observable dot merge and we can pass in
source one and source - alright and
let's add dot take 25 and then we'll
subscribe I keep doing that
okay so let's go ahead and save that and
now we'll see Marge two starts because
it's every half second and then every
two seconds merge once Marge one emits
its value okay and this is a better way
to do it we're creating the two sources
then we're calling rx observable merge
and passing in those sources okay so now
let's take a look at concat now the
difference between merge and concat is
that concat will go one after another
all right so what I'm going to do is
just copy what we just did here I'm
sorry right here all right and we're not
going to do interval if we do that it's
just going to go on forever so I think a
better example would be to use range
okay so we'll say range and let's do
zero five all right and then the mapping
will change that - we'll just say source
1 and source 2 okay this one will also
be range but this one we want to set to
6 and we'll go to 11 all right no not to
11 we want to go up 5 all right and then
down here we're going to say rx
observable dot can cat source one source
2 and we're going to get rid of the take
operator and let's see what that gives
us all right so if we look it says
source 1 it's going to go 0 and then 5
up okay and then it concatenates this
one which goes from 6 up 5 to 10 all
right so it runs one after another while
merge will run at the same exact time
all right so that's the biggest
difference between the two all right so
that's merge and kin cat now let's take
a look at merge map can cat map and
switch map
all right so now we're going to take a
look at merge Maps which map and can cat
map and what these do is they
essentially stop us from having to
subscribe to nest subscribes all right
now if you remember back when we worked
with the github example we did a double
subscribe which we shouldn't do so let's
take a look at what we shouldn't do
alright so say our X dot observable dot
of and let's just say hello all right
and then we're going to subscribe to
that and in the SUBSCRIBE we'll say V
and then we'll do another observable
okay observable dot of and then we want
to use that value that V that's returned
and we're going to just concatenate onto
it
everyone alright and then we subscribe
to that okay so when we subscribe to it
let's just do X and you'll say
console.log X all right so you probably
know what's going to happen or we're
going to get hello everyone all right so
this is something you may want to do you
haven't observable and then you want to
use that value that you get from the
observable that data in another one and
this isn't the right way to do it now it
works in this situation but there's
others where it's not going to work okay
if you want to put this in a variable
and reuse it in certain places you're
going to have some problems alright so
what we're going to do here is use merge
map so let's do the same thing using
merge map will say observable dot of
hello all right and then what we want to
do is say dot
merge map and then in here we'll have
we'll save V and return ok we want to
return our X dot 0 lot of and in here
we'll say V whoops everyone yeah that's
right and then we'll subscribe to it
alright so now we'll comment this one
out and save and we should get the same
thing hello everyone
alright so this is the correct way to do
it so now let's take a look at switch
map which basically transforms the items
that are emitted by an observable into
observables and then flattens the
emissions
all right into a single observable now
this used to be called flat map in rxjs
4 ok which is now switch map so what I'm
going to do is I'm going to use it on
the github example that we did so I'm
going to paste in that exact code and
let me just comment this out ok I'm
going to paste in that code and then
we're going to basically clean it up a
little all right so let's we have this
get user that's going to stay the same
but down here let's redo this to be a
little bit more clean so let's take this
right here and paste it down here and
we'll work from that I'm going to make
this a little wider okay so I want to
add on to this now see how we're doing
this get user and then a target value
let's go ahead and map our value that's
emitted to that so go ahead and say dot
map
II and then we'll set that to e dot
target dot value so now we don't have to
worry about the target dot value anymore
it's going to be mapped to the actual
emission all right so after that let's
do dot switch map and in here we'll
paste in our value then we're going to
grab this
it's from promise copy that and we have
to return it so return and then we'll
paste that in okay and then we can just
use V right here because we already
mapped it to the target value and then
we can put a semicolon and then let's
subscribe to it okay and I can actually
copy what we have in this right here
alright so let's go ahead and comment
that out
save it okay so now we'll go ahead and
type and it works all right so this is a
much better way to do it okay so this
video went long as usual went longer
than I had planned so sorry about that
hopefully you learned at least the the
gist of how reactive extensions works
this was all very practical basic stuff
we did I will be making a video in the
future where we can actually build a
working application using reactive
extensions all right so thanks for
hanging on this long and hopefully
enjoyed it please subscribe leave a like
leave a comment if you had any issues or
whatever you can do is fine and I would
suggest also checking out the edge wanax
course alright thanks for watching I'll
see you next time